# Jiawei Gu

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/jiawei-gu/ | GitHub: https://github.com/jiawku

Cell: (801)-637-4021 | Email: jiawku17@gmail.com | Salt Lake City, UT

# **Summary**

I am a fours years experienced bioinformatician in academic and industry. I obtained a **MS in biology** and a **MS in computer science** from University of Texas at Dallas. It gives me advantage in combining biology knowledge with programming skills in data engineering and analysis. With a Certificate from **Amazon Web Service**, I can boost your development and production in the era of cloud.

## **Work Experience**

### Bioinformatics Analyst, Navican Genomics, Inc. Salt Lake City, 08/2018-Present

#### Production & Automation

- Daily clinical control sequencing quality assurance.
- Implemented and improved the Tumor Mutation Burden(TMB) calculation algorithm within the bioinformatics team inspired by
- Built an automated pipeline for clinical control assurance in python. It connected multiple cloud service platforms(Philips IntelliSpace Genomics Medicine, SalesForce, SeraCare IQ, Slack, and Amazon AWS) via API.
- Created an Illumina BaseSpace Native APP for sequencing quality control using Docker.

### Data Engineering

- Created tools to query and clean data from cloud service platforms (Philips IntelliSpace Genomics Medicine, SalesForce, Clarity LIMS) via API for ETL and R&D.
- Designed a Bioinformatics Variant Database to store clinical mutations.

## Data Analysis

- Implemented and run validation workflows for Illumina TruSight™ Tumor 170 Sequencing Assay.
- Designed statistical tests for lab operation quality metrics.
- Help with other ad-hoc data analysis requests.

#### Research Assistant, Biology Department, UTD 01/2014-12/2016

I focused on the research of Next-Generation Sequencing analysis, especially on ChIP-seq, RNA-seq, and ChIA-PET Seq result analysis, and using machine learning tools to analysze and predict from data.

- Machine Learning Prediction for RNA-chromosome interaction
  - Collect **genomic and epigenomic data** from online resources by a self coded **web crawler**.
  - Cleaned data and used Random Shuffle to generate more negative data points.
  - Applied Support Vector Machine() to generate a model
- DNA Sequencing Analysis of Brg1 in Cancer Cell, UTD
  - o Built pipelines for data process and ChIP-seg analysis using Linux bash shell
  - o Implemented a protein binding motif scan and enrichment analysis program in R
  - Analyzed and Visualized data in R and Python
  - **Article publication**: Shi, X., et al. "SMARCA4/Brg1 coordinates genetic and epigenetic networks underlying Shh-type medulloblastoma development." Oncogene (2016).

## **Skills**

### Programming languages

Python, Java, JavaScript, R, SAS, SQL

## Machine Learning & Statistical model

Support Vector Machine (SVM), Random Forest, Deep Learning, Hidden Markov Model (HMM), Expectation Maximization(EM)

### NGS(Next Generation Sequencing) Analysis

ChIP-Seq Analysis ,RNA-Seq Analysis, GATK toolkit ,Gene Ontology Enrichment Analysis, ChIA-PET Analysis, Motif Analysis

#### Frameworks & Tools

- BigData: Apache Spark, Apache Hadoop
- Web: MEAN stack(MongoDB, Express JS, Angular JS, Node.js), Java Spring
- Deep Learning: TensorFlow, Keras
- · Containerization: Docker, Kubernetes
- Cloud Service: Amazon Web Service(certified)

## Certification

· AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate

Credential ID: 6WQVVZSKE24EQLK9

- Coursera Deep Learning Specialization
- SAS Certified Base & Advanced Programmer for SAS 9
- edX Verified Certificate for Big Data Analysis with Apache Spark

## **Education**

01/2017-05/2018

MS, Computer Science; University of Texas at Dallas(UTD); 3.91/4

08/2013-12/2016

**MS, Bioinformatics**; University of Texas at Dallas(UTD); **3.73/4** Performed two and a half years (05/2014 -12/2016) of studies in pursuit of Ph.D.

# **Side Project**

### Dog Breed Identification, Kaggle.com 05/2018

- · A Kaggle machine learning competition Project
- Design and built a convolutional neural network(CNN) in keras to determine the breed of a dog in an image
- Applied a integrated model of Xception and InceptionV3 to extract bottleneck features from image
- Used three fully connected layers with drop out and batch normalization to get predicted probabilities
- Used Adam optimilization algorithm to train the final model with cross entropy as loss function
- Get the final validation accuracy of 99.76%, rank 102 out of 1286 teams\*\*